<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Scipio's dreame. Or The statesman's extasie Wherein is contayned an epitomie of all the sciences, naturall, morall, and supernaturall. Tending to proue the immortalitie of the soule, as the proper merit of iustice.</title>
            <author>Cicero, Marcus Tullius.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1627</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18885</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5318</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118636</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853843</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853843</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19241</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18885)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19241)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1062:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Scipio's dreame. Or The statesman's extasie Wherein is contayned an epitomie of all the sciences, naturall, morall, and supernaturall. Tending to proue the immortalitie of the soule, as the proper merit of iustice.</title>
                  <author>Cicero, Marcus Tullius.</author>
                  <author>E. C. S., fl. 1627.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 30 p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B. A[lsop] and T. Fawcet, for L. C[hapman] and are to be sold at his shop at Chancery Lane end,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1627.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's and bookseller's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Translator's dedication signed: E.C.S.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The dreame of Scipio.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="lat">lat</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Neoplatonism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19241:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19241:1"/>
            <p>SCIPIO'S <hi>Dreame.</hi> OR THE STATES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MAN'S EXTASIE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>WHEREIN</hi> IS CONTAYNED AN Epitomie of all the Sciences, <hi>Naturall, Morall,</hi> and <hi>Supernaturall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tending to proue the Immortalitie of the SOVLE, as the proper merit of IVSTICE.</p>
            <q>Superſtes durat post hominem Juſtitia.</q>
            <p>LONDON. Printed by <hi>B. A.</hi> and <hi>T. Fawcet,</hi> for <hi>L. C.</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at <hi>Chancery</hi> Lane end. 1627.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19241:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19241:2"/>
            <head>TO HIS HONOV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RED KINSMAN FRANCIS FVLLVVAR <hi>Eſquire.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat I Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate this to your Graui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, is not that I arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate ought to my owne abilitie, But to pay you the tribute of a Kinſman, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the tye of Nature, which
<pb facs="tcp:19241:3"/> ſo otderly linketh all dependancy thereof, as we ſee each thing hath ſome reference one to another. The Elements are joyned by Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolization, the Ayre to the Fire by warmneſſe, the Water to the Ayre by moyſture, the Earth to the Water by coldneſſe. And theſe my not yet ſufficiently ripe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauours to your mature judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which though in moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equall proportion in regard of Time (not hauing attayned <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dullam</hi> SVADAE, yet the honour I beare to MINERVA will (I hope) bring them neare to your acceptance; The rather for that you will giue entertaynment to the Author, whoſe worke is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
<pb facs="tcp:19241:3"/> of your welcome, becauſe it treateth of the reward proper to ſuch as your ſelfe, that haue ſpent the prime of your yeares in doing your Countrey ſeruice: And ſo conſequently to the Tranſlation, which I lay in the lap of your Loue and Patronage, leaſt any Harpie ſhould meet with it, being in a homely weed. But could I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorne it with APOLLO'S golden coate, or AESCVLAPIVS golden beard, It ſhould wayte vpon your fauor, And my ſelfe ſhall doe you the ſeruice of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your very louing Kinſman to command: <hi>E. C. S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:19241:4"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>OVRTEOVS READER;</hi> Hee that doth not ayme at the higheſt pitch of perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, can neuer attayne to the loweſt degree there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; which gaue mee incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, though yet but in the Infancy of the <hi>Muſes</hi> to vndertake this taske, which howſoeuer my paines proue accepted of, yet I am confident, for the worth of the firſt Writer, it will find fauorers. And though it come not apparelled with the Maieſty of a Courtly robe, yet I hope it hath an honeſt Countrey comeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. And my deſire to communicate it to ſuch as knew it not in the Naturall and Nationall habit thereof, will gaine a fauourable conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction that it commeth in our Engliſh attire, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the matter thereof is for all men, for all times, full of compleat and eminent know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge:
<pb facs="tcp:19241:4"/> and the rather becauſe this, amongſt many of that Noble and wiſe mans workes hath not come to light in our language, for ought I euer knew, yet is it of merit in the firſt place, and eſpecially when many men now a dayes do ſleepe out their dayes not dreaming of the reward in the Life immortall, which the wiſe Heathen did propound to themſelues as incitements to graue republiquiſts to take care, <hi>Nequid detrimenti, reſpublica capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at.</hi> And it may moue ſome more lofty tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſpirit to lend his tongue in a ſtraine more lofty. And becauſe great matters cannot bee expected from blooming yeares, my duty ſhall be diſcharged, if my diligence be not ſcorned; For <hi>Non debent, qui magna preſtare ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queunt, parua negligere.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:19241:5"/>
            <q>
               <l>Wiſe <hi>SCIPIO</hi> ſleepes in Heauenly rapture's Dreame</l>
               <l>Thou Stateſ-man Just, thy ſelfe like happie deeme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of Scipio sleeping</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19241:5"/>
            <head>THE DREAME <hi>of</hi> SCIPIO <hi>taken out</hi> of the ſixt Booke of <hi>Cicero de Republica.</hi>
            </head>
            <head>
               <hi>SCIPIO</hi> the perſon.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat time I came into <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frica,</hi> (MAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIVS MANI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIVS, beeing <hi>Conſul</hi>) Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander in chiefe (as yee know)
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19241:6"/> to the fourth Legion, there was nothing I more deſired, then that I might meet MASSINIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SA, a King moſt friendly to our Family for juſt cauſes. Whom when I repaired vnto the old King imbracing mee wept with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and ſoone after beholding the Heauens with caſt vp eyes, vttered theſe words; O ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Sunne, I giue thee hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thankes, and all the Coeleſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all creatures, that before I finiſh this tranſitory life, with theſe eyes I doe ſee, in mine owne Kingdome, and in mine owne houſe, PVBLIVS CORNELIVS SCIPIO, whoſe very name doth reuiue my ſpirits: Therefore the memory of that excellent and inuincible man ſhall neuer depart out of my mind.</p>
            <p>When I had enquired the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19241:6"/> of his Kingdome, and hee of our Common-wealth, much ſpeech hauing paſſed on both ſides, the day was ſpent, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward being entertained with a Princely ſupper, wee prolon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged our diſcourſe the moſt part of the night: When the good old King would moue ſpeech of nothing, but of AFRICANVS, who remembred not onely all his deeds, but alſo his words: This done, ſo ſoone as wee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted to bed, I being weary with my trauell, and becauſe I had watched very late, a ſleepe more heauy then vſuall ſeized on mee.<note place="margin">Father to <hi>SCIPIO.</hi>
               </note> AFRICANVS (I thinke out of that, which wee had ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: for it commonly commeth to paſſe, that our cogitation and communication doe bring forth ſome ſuch thing in our ſleepe, as
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19241:7"/> ENNIVS writeth of HOMER, of whom waking hee vſed often to thinke and ſpeake,) I ſay, AFRICANVS in ſuch a ſhape preſented himſelfe vnto mee, as I knew him better by his repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation, then as hee was here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore liuing (or in his body.) Whom ſo ſoone as I perceiued, I trimbled with feare, but he ſaid vnto mee, O SCIPIO, bee at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiue, feare not, and what I ſhall tell you, lay vp in your mind. Doe you ſee yonder Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which being compelled by mee to obey the people of <hi>Rome,</hi> reneweth the old warre, nor can it reſt in peace, (For he did point vnto me that ancient Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>Carthage,</hi> from an high place, full of Starres, gliſtring, and bright) to which you now come to lay Seige, ſcarce yet dignified
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19241:7"/> with military honour. Within theſe two yeares you ſhall Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer it, being <hi>Conſull,</hi> and this ſurname which now you haue by inheritance, ſhall be your owne by purchaſe. And when you haue ſacked the Towne, you ſhall be carryed in triumph, and be created <hi>Cenſor,</hi> and goe an Ambaſſadour to <hi>Egipt, Syria, Aſia,</hi> and <hi>Grecia,</hi> and in your abſence ſhall againe be elected <hi>Conſul,</hi> you ſhall wage a great war, and you ſhall raze <hi>Numan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia.</hi> Bur when in your Charyot you ſhall be carryed to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitoll, you will find the common wealth diſturbed by the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailes of my Nephew. Heere<note place="margin">SCIPIO <hi>ſurnamed</hi> AFRICA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NVS.</note> AFRICANVS, you muſt ſhew to your Countrey, the luſter of your ſpirit, wit, and wiſedome. But at that time I perceiue a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19241:8"/> doubtfull courſe, as it were of the fates. For when you ſhall be ſeauen times eight yeares of age, and theſe two numbers, of which either is accounted a full num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, the one for one cauſe, the other for another, ſhall make vp the fatall account by a naturall reuolution. Vpon you alone, and vpon your name the whole City ſhall relye it ſelfe: the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, all good men, your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates, and the <hi>Latines</hi> ſhall fixe their eyes vpon you: you ſhall be the onely man, on whoſe endeuors the ſafegard of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhall depend. To be ſhort, it is expedient, that you being Dictator ſhall gouerne the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, if you can eſcape the vngodly hands of your kindſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. Heere when LELIVS gaue an out-cry, and the reſt of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19241:8"/> them groaned; SCIPIO gently ſmiling, ſaid, awake me not from my Dreame and let all be at peace. Heare the reſt. But that you may be encouraged to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Common-wealth, O AFRICANVS, ſo perſwade your ſelfe, that for all thoſe, who haue preſerued, ſuccoured, and ayded their Country, there is a place de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed and appointed in Heauen, where the bleſſed ſhall inioy E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity. For there is nothing, that on the earth can be done, more acceptable to that great God, who gouerneth this whole world, then Conſultations, and Congregations aſſotiated vnder a Law, which are called Cities. The Gouernours and maintay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners hereof deſcended from hence, and hither ſhall returne.</p>
            <p>Heere, although I was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19241:9"/> not ſo much with the dread of Death, as the Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies of mine owne kindred, yet I demanded, if hee liued, and Father<note place="margin">Father to him, and Grandfather to <hi>SCIPIO.</hi>
               </note> PAVLLVS, and others, whom wee thought ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct: Yes truely, ſayd hee, they liue, who haue fledde from the bonds of the Body, as if it were out of Priſon; for that which is called your Life, is Death. But ſee, Father PAVLLVS is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming vnto you; whom ſo ſoone as I beheld, I powred out a ſtreame of teares. But hee hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding mee in his armes, and kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing me, bid mee to bridle my paſſion: So ſoone as I could refraine from teares, and was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſpeake; I ſayd, I beſeech you moſt holy and happie Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſith this is Life, as I heare AFRICANVS tell, why doe I
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19241:9"/> abide on the earth, and haſten not rather to come thither to you?<note place="margin">PAVLLVS.</note> Hee replyed, things are not ſo ordered; For vnleſſe GOD, euen hee, whoſe Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple this Vniuerſe is, which you behold, ſhall free you from thoſe priſons of the Body, there can bee no entrance for you hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For this is the condition, vnder which they are borne, who inhabite that Globe you ſee in the middle of this Temple, which is called the Earth: And to theſe is Life giuen, out of thoſe Eternall lights, which yee call Starres and Planets, who being round, and formed like a Ball, inlined with Diuine intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, doe runne their courſe and compaſſe with wonderfull ſwiftneſſe. Wherefore, both you, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> PVELIVS! and all god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19241:10"/> men, muſt retayne your life within the cuſtody of the Body. Neyther may wee paſſe from this tranſitory life, without his Command, from whom wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued it. Leaſt wee ſeeme to ſhun that humaine eſtate, which is ordayned for vs of GOD.<note place="margin">AFRICA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NVS <hi>ſpeech.</hi>
               </note> But ſee, O SCIPIO! that you ſo loue Iuſtice and Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as this thy Granfather, and I thy Father who begat thee: which being ſo great in thy Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and Allies, is alſo moſt excellent in thy Country: And that Life leadeth vnto Heauen, and into the ſociety of thoſe, who lately liued, and being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered from the body, doe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habit that place. (Now that was a circle gliſtring among the Stars with a reſplendant bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes) which you call <hi>Orbis Lacte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:19241:10"/> or the milky Circle (as yee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued it from the Grecians.) From whence I deeply contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plating all the reſt did ſeeme paſſing excellent, and to be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered at. But theſe Starres were ſuch as wee neuer beheld out of this place, and there magnitudes ſuch as we neuer ſuſpected, of whom that was the leaſt, which being loweſt in Heauen, the nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to the Earth ſhined with a borrowed light.<note place="margin">Luna citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma terris.</note> And the globes of the Starres did exceed the greatneſſe of the Earth. But now that Earth it ſelfe doth ſeeme ſo ſmall, as I repine at our Empire, wherein we doe touch but as it were a point thereof. Which when I more earneſtly beheld, AFRICANVS ſaid, I pray you, how long will your mind be faſtened on the Earth.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19241:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> Doe you not behold, what holy habitations you ſhall come into? All things are connexed to you by mine Orbes, or rather by nine Globes.</p>
            <p>Whereof one is the heauenly vppermoſt, which inuolueth all the reſt, that ſupreame<note place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</note> GOD mouing and containing the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. In which are infixed thoſe euer continewed courſes of the Starres which runne round and returne to their firſt motion: Vnder which there are ſeauen others, that go backward with a contrary motion to the courſe of Heauen. Among which ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, that within the Earth they call <hi>Saturne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Saturnus.</note> doth poſſeſſe one Globe.</p>
            <p>Next vnto that, is the bright Starre which is called <hi>Iupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iupiter.</note> (in aſpect) happie and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19241:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> proſperous vnto Man-kind.</p>
            <p>Then the fiery and dreadfull Starre which yee call <hi>Mars.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mars.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Next almoſt vnder the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle Region,<note place="margin">Sol.</note> the <hi>Sunne</hi> is pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, beeing the guide, and cheife gouernour of all the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Starres, the ſoule and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perature of the World, ſuch in magnitude, as it lightneth, and repleniſheth all things with the brightneſſe thereof. The motion of <hi>Venus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus.</note> and the moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Mercurius</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mercurius.</note> doe follow this Planet, as if they were his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions. And <hi>Luna</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luna.</note> increaſing her light by the beames of the Sunne, doth make her Changes in the loweſt Orbe. Below the Moone there is nothing, but what is ſubiect to Death and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay, excepting Soules beſtowed on Mankind by the guift of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19241:12"/> Gods.<note place="margin">Tellus.</note> For that which is the middle, and the ninth; to wit, the Earth is not moued, and is vnder the reſt, and all weighty things are carryed downeward to it by their owne motion.</p>
            <p>Which when with amazed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe I did view, as ſoone as I came to my ſelfe, what, Oh what ſound! (ſaid I) ſo ſhrill and ſweet doth fill mine cares. Euen this,<note place="margin">Coeli harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia.</note> ſaid hee, which joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with diſlike diſtances, but yet according to their proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on diſtinguiſhed in meaſure, is made by the vehement force and motion of thoſe Orbes: and tempering ſharpes with flats, keeping equall time maketh va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious harmony. For neyther can ſo great motions ariſe out of ſilence: And beſide, Nature ſo directeth it, that the outmoſt on
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19241:12"/> the one part ſound flats, but ſharpes on the other part. For which cauſe the higheſt courſe of the ſtarrified Heauen, whoſe conuerſion is ſwifter, is moued with a ſharpe and ſhrill ſound: but this Orbe of the Moone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing loweſt, hath his motion with a deepe flat.<note place="margin">Terra noua.</note> For the Earth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ninth, remayning im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moueable, alwayes ſubſiſteth in the loweſt place, contayning the middle of the world. But thoſe eight motions, among which, two of them haue equall force,<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus, &amp; Mercurius.</note> make ſeauen Sounds diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in their diſtances, which number is the perfection almoſt of all things. The which, learned men imitating with their muſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Inſtruments and ſongs, haue gayned recourſe for themſelues to this place, as others, who with
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19241:13"/> their rare wits in that corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble life, haue exerciſed Diuine ſtudies.</p>
            <p>With this ſound your eares be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing filled were made deafe: (ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is any ſence more dull in you) as whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Nilus</hi> powreth down water-floods headlong from the higheſt Mountaynes to thoſe places, which yee call <hi>Catadupa,</hi> the Inhabitants of that place, are depriued of the ſence of Hearing, by reaſon of the hide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſound. And this ſound is ſo great by the moſt ſwift mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the world, as the eares of man cannot beare it; euen as no man can looke againſt the Sun, and as by the beames thereof your ſight, and ſence is maſtered.</p>
            <p>Being ſtrooke with admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe things, yet I fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19241:13"/> mine eyes (thus aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) on the Earth. Then ſaid A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FRICANVS, I perceiue, euen now you muſe on the ſeate and houſe of man; which if it ſeeme ſo little to you, as indeed it is, euer caſt vp your eyes to theſe Celeſtiall things, and diſpiſe thoſe Earthly. For what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne can you obtayne from the mouth of Man, or what lookt for Glory can you enioy? you ſee men doe inhabit theſe ſtreight and narrow places in the Earth, and in thoſe ſpotts (as it were) vaſt wilderneſſes are interpoſed betweene their habitations: They alſo that dwell vpon the Earth are ſo interrupted that there can bee no traffique or intercourſe from one to another, but ſome doe ſide you, ſome doe thwart
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19241:14"/> you, and ſome are oppoſite to you, from whome indeed you can expect no glory. For you perceiue that ſame Earth to bee girded,<note place="margin">Zonae.</note> and incloſed about as if it were with certaine belts: Among which, you ſee two farre diſtant one from another, and vnderpropped on both ſides with thoſe poles of Heauen, are extreame cold in tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: but the middle one, and the greateſt be ſcorched with the vehement heat of the Sunne: two are habitable: whereof that South-ward (in which the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that dwell,<note place="margin">Antipodes.</note> goe with their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eet aduerſe to yours) belongeth not to that kind of men where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of of you are. But this <hi>Northren Zone,</hi> which yee inhabit, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, how ſmall a part of it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h vnto you. For all that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19241:14"/> earth, which yee dwell on, being narrow in the toppe, wider on the ſides, is a certaine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ittle Iland incloſed about with the Sea, which yee (tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> liue on the Land) call the <hi>Athlantick</hi> Sea, the maine, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d the <hi>Ocean.</hi> Which though it haue ſo great a name, you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee how little it is. Of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heſe inhabited, and known<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lands hath the fame of any of our Anceſtors been a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e to tranſcend the Mount <hi>Caucaſus,</hi> (now in your ſight) or ſayle ouer <hi>Ganges?</hi> who ſhall heare of your name in the far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt parts of the Eaſt, or the vtmoſt parts of the Weſt, the North, or South? which being cut off, you ſee aſſuredly, in how ſmall compaſſe your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne is dilated. And they that ſpeake of your Name, of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19241:15"/> what continuance will it bee? Beſide, if the off-ſpring of thoſe that ſhall ſucceed vs, haue a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to tell to their Poſterity our prayſes, as they heard from their Anceſtors, yet, for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luges, and Conflagrations of the world: which of neceſſitie muſt happen at the appointed time, wee can not obtaine not onely euerlaſting, but no long laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing glory. For what matters it, that they who ſhall bee borne hereafter, ſhall ſpeake of thee, when there is none left, of whom they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended: who neyther were fewer in number, and certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly were of better condition? Eſpecially, when not one of them, by whome our Name (or glory) may bee heard of, can beare one Age in memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19241:15"/> for men commonly rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon an Age by the recourſe (or reuolution) of the Sunne which is of one Starre.</p>
            <p>But when all the Starres ſhall reuolue to the ſame point, from whence they firſt moued, and ſhall bring about (or accompliſh) the whole Heauens compaſſe (or circumference) with the long intercourſes thereof, then that may bee truely called <hi>Annus vertens</hi> (or a perfit yeare) wherein I dare ſcarce tell, how many Ages of men are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined. For as in times paſt the Sunne ſeemed to men to bee loſt and extinguiſhed, what time the Soule of ROMVLVS penetrated theſe Temples: when both in the ſame point (of Heauen) and at the ſame
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19241:16"/> ſeaſon the Sunne ſhall againe bee loſt; when all the Starres and Signes are brought backe to their firſt Originall, count that a perfit yeare.</p>
            <p>But of this yeare, know, the twentieth part is not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed. Therefore if you diſpaire a re-entrance into this place, where Worthy and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent men enioy all things, of how ſmall a ſcantling is that glory of men, which can ſcarce attayne (or extend to) the ſmall part of but one Age? If then you will enter into a higher conſideration, and lift vp your eyes to this Mantion and Eternall habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; you ſhall neither giue eare to the words of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people, nor repoſe the hope of your eſtate in any
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19241:16"/> mans rewards. It beſt becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth you to bee led on by the allurements of Vertue to true Honour: Let others looke to it (or take heed) what they ſay of you (yet they will ſtill bee tatling, and babling.) For all their talke is confined to the narrow ſtreights of theſe Regions, which you behold, nor hath it beene durable of any; and is buryed in the Graues of men, and vtterly aboliſhed by the obliuion of Poſterity.</p>
            <p>All which when hee had vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, I replyed, O AFRICA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NVS! ſith to theſe that are of good deſert; there is, from their Country bounds and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits layd open for a paſſage into Heauen; though from my very Cradle (hauing tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19241:17"/> the ſteps of my forefathers and your ſelfe, I haue not beene awanting to fill vp the meaſure of your Honour, yet now vpon the propounding of ſuch ample reward, I will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply my ſelfe with farre more vigilancy.</p>
            <p>And hee reioyned, doe but your endeauour, and take this from mee, you your ſelfe are not mortall, but this bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of yours; neither are you the ſame, which your out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhape doth perſonate: but the mind of euery man is his abſolute ſelfe, not that figure, or forme, which may bee pointed to with the finger. Therefore know thou art a GOD, becauſe hee is a GOD, who hath life, ſence, memory, and foreſight: who
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19241:17"/> doth guide, gouerne, and moue that body ouer which hee hath rule or dominion, as well as that great GOD himſelfe doth this whole world; And as that euerli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing GOD doth moue this world which is in ſome part lyable to mortallity: ſo doth the neuer dying Soule, of the body, which is ſubiect to frailty. For that is Eternall, which is euer in motion. And that which bringeth motion to any thing is euer in motion: But that which is moued from ſome other thing, when the motion is ended it muſt of neceſſity haue end of liuing. That onely therefore, which moueth it ſelfe, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is neuer forſaken of it ſelfe, doth in like ſort neuer
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19241:18"/> ceaſe to moue. Moreouer that is the fountaine, that is the beginning to all the reſt, which are moued.</p>
            <p>Now to that, which is the beginning, there is no Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall; for all things ſprung (or are deriued) out of that which is the beginning; but it out of nothing. For that could not bee a beginning, which were begotten of another: And if it neuer haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, nor can it at any time haue ending: for a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning being ended or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct, can neuer it ſelfe from any other take a new be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning; nor of it ſelfe cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate another thing: becauſe it is of neceſſity that all things ſhould grow out of that which is the firſt beginning.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:19241:18"/>
            <p>So as it commeth to paſſe, that the beginning of motion is from that which moueth it ſelfe, of, or by it ſelfe. And that can neither haue begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning nor ending. Elſe of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty the whole Heauens muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay or fall, and all <hi>Nature</hi> bee at a ſtand, nor can it obtaine any vigour (or power) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it may bee moued from the firſt mouer (or motion.)</p>
            <p>Therefore ſith it is manifeſt, That is Eternall, which hath its motion from its ſelfe: who is hee, that denyeth this <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> (or condition) to bee attributed to our Soules? For euery thing is without Soule, which is agitated with an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall motion: but that which is the Soule is ſtirred with an internall motion, and that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19241:19"/> of its owne, For this is the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> and Power proper to the Soule.</p>
            <p>Which if of all other things it bee the onely one thing that doth moue it ſelfe: certaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is not borne, but is Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.</p>
            <p>Buiſy this in the beſt cares. And the beſt cares are thoſe, which conſiſt in the ſafeguard of your Country, about which your mind being imployed and applyed, will more ſwift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mount into this Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Mantion, and that will ſooner come to paſſe, if very now, while it is inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the body, it ſhall tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend the world, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templating theſe things, which ſhall bee Eternall, retyre it ſelfe ſpeedily from the body.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:19241:19"/>
            <p>For the Soules of thoſe, who haue giuen themſelues to the pleaſures of the body, and haue manifeſted themſelues, as it were ſeruants to them, and by the prouocations of Luſts, ſubdued to thoſe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, haue violated the lawes of GOD and Man; when they are lapſed out of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, are toſſed too and fro about the Earth, and neuer returne (or re-aſcend) into this place, vntill they haue beene turmoyled many Ages.</p>
            <p>So hee vaniſhed, and I from my Dreame awaked.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:19241:20"/>
            <head>A Corollary.</head>
            <l>AS doth a Dreame;</l>
            <l>or as a tale that's told,</l>
            <l>So vaniſheth man's Life:</l>
            <l>and All is gone.</l>
            <l>Conſuls and Common-people</l>
            <l>are Enrowl'd</l>
            <l>Within Death's List:</l>
            <l>Virtue ſuruiues Alone.</l>
            <l>So <hi>Wiſedome, Iuſtice,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Meekneſſe, Fortitude,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Are Crowned: when</l>
            <l>this <hi>Chaos</hi> is ſubdued.</l>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19241:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
